And welcome to the Operators podcast.
I'm here with Mike and Matt on our
wonderful Wednesday as we do our
podcast, and we're going to talk about
something that
is very apparent. We had I was in Miami
last week, guys, and I had to rush back
to do the podcast because I wanted to
show, if you're watching this on video,
that I have a manufacturing behind me.
And it's a big one, 280,000 square foot,
and I want to talk because one of the
most common things that I'm asked,
because I do have manufacturing in
Mexico, is
why did you do it in Mexico? Why do you
manufacture your own product? Do you
make more money because of it? Is it
awesome? Is it a pain in the ass? How
does it help you? Are Are you an idiot
for even trying it? I was in Miami with
all these guys selling supplements, and
they have like teams of like one, two,
or three people trying to sell their
stuff, and I've got 1,400 people in my
company. So, we want to talk through
this so everyone out there that has a
business from one to 100 million can
decide if they want to get involved in a
larger, vertically integrated type of a
business. Now,
>> Oh, god.
>> I know. I know. Matt,
>> is yes to everything. It's stupid. It's
awesome. It's fast.
It's just Yes.
>> [laughter]
>> Okay, so like I did it in Mexico, you
did it in Canada. Tell me about why and
when and a little bit about this cuz I
don't know history of this.
>> Oh, oh, I mean, my my perspective is I
just I'm clairvoyant. I knew AI was
coming 8 years ago.
Uh and I knew that it I wanted to be
high asset and low obsolescence. That's
it. I'm a freaking genius.
No, that's not it.
>> How many people do you have? Like, how
big of it is? Do you go into the
manufacturing every day? What do you do?
>> No, dude. So, our headquarters and our
facility are actually separate by about,
I think, 8 miles.
Um so, there's people going back and
forth all the time.
We opened
like office first, manufacturing came, I
think, a year or two later.
It was out of necessity. Uh, we just
our category has got like a skew
complexity
and a planned obsolescence with phone
models every year. So, like the phone
release cycle is brutal. Um,
and that once we got into once I got
into the business, this is like where
ignorance is not your best friend. I got
into the the business and started to
realize just how bad everybody's balance
sheet was in this industry with
inventory
and how like this is how companies die.
And that opening a factory became a uh
an absolute like you have to do this.
Like this is the only way this business
works on paper. Uh, I've heard Mike say
this before, where like if you can't
make a business make sense in a in a
spreadsheet, it's probably not going to
make sense in real life. Like it just
didn't make sense.
I was watching like inventory grow.
Apple would release a new phone model
and new capacity. And you never knew
which phone was going to sell well of
all the ones they released. Same with
Google, same with Samsung. So, the whole
thing was just such a mess in the back
end that
we didn't have a choice. And now we have
a factory in Canada, here where I live
in Kelowna. Um,
and then we have a new one in Mesa in
Arizona.
So, two factories uh at this point. And
that's just,
you know, growth, demand, got to got to
fill it somehow. Um,
but I think the cool thing is like I
think somewhere between like 80 and 90%
of all of the product we ship now in
North America is made here.
And uh unlike a lot of companies, our
resins are also American.
So,
our supply chain is weirdly
American. Like we we don't get a lot of
things from outside of the US.
>> Well, I mean, the necessity thing is the
the thing that jumped out at me because
everyone's like, "Hey, why did you
create North America's largest leather
bag manufacturing?" It's because I was
just stupid enough to do it. And when we
went to suppliers with all my demands,
no one wanted to give me everything I
wanted. I wanted a few of these to test,
but with the ability to scale. I wanted
the best prices. I wanted them to treat
me like the king. And they're like,
"Hey, you're one of many. And we have no
belief that you're actually going to
grow." I was a guy in a garage calling
people up saying, "Can you make for me?"
And they're saying, I I remember being
on my front lawn walking around
pretending I was bigger than I was to
people to try to get them to do my this.
So, I started doing it out of necessity.
And then I grew out of necessity. Like,
"What do you do there in Oklahoma other
than run Oklahoma?"
>> Everywhere we turn right now, there is
some world-changing AI announcement. And
I think the trick for us operators is
figuring out what's actually going to
help our business. Is this stuff saving
us money? Is it helping us grow revenue?
Is it helping us grow profit? Like,
where is the freaking ROI? Jason for
Hexclad, tell everybody what is actually
working for you guys.
>> Yeah, look, I'm laser-like focused on
implementing AI wherever we can to just
make us more efficient. Fulfill has been
huge for us. Like, my team is constantly
using Fulfill's new CLI tool and MCP
features with Quad. They're now able to
query Fulfill data. They They can buy
code up dashboards.
Um I mean, we get these awesome
dashboards on operations and and Fulfill
continues to build things that are
actually
useful for brands. It's hard to see what
kind of AI work is valuable and what
isn't. Sure, like there's so much out
there, so much coming at us, but Fulfill
seems to be giving us things we can
really use
to get more efficient.
>> Um well, I I do occasionally try and
sell drinkware,
uh, as well. The, uh uh,
we really started to look at
manufacturing. So, we we import our
industry, as I've described before, is
like 95% of it's made in a very small
geographic area in China.
Um, and this is not uncommon. You have
these kind of, um, cottage industries
where all of the the world's supply of
like, we've talked about this before,
Wuhan happened to have a ton of the
world's supply of wedding dresses. And
so, when Wuhan got shut down, it was
like you couldn't get a wedding dress.
And this is the same deal with stainless
steel insulated drinkware. So,
there there really weren't options, and
that didn't bother us until
COVID. Because during COVID, uh,
you know, the supply chain was an
absolute disaster, shipping rates went
through the roof, and it was as much
about reliably having access to your
product as it was even about cost. So,
um, I think depending on the industry
you're in, it can be a cost play to
vertically integrate.
But, it's also like a risk mitigation
that if you can't get your product, then
your company dies that way.
And believe it or not, that's how some
companies have died, that they just
weren't able to get their product for
whatever reason.
So, we started looking at it in, I would
say, 2020,
uh, 2021, we made a major investment,
probably on the order of 5 to 8 million
dollars. Happy to report, we probably
set most of that on fire trying to,
figure out, I mean,
>> [laughter]
>> um,
probably about a Miami townhouse worth
of, uh, tuition [laughter]
paid
in the manufacturing pursuit. Um, and
and I think we we learned a lot of the
reasons along the way why it's difficult
to manufacture in America, and
it's kind of like when somebody comes to
me with a business idea and says, "I've
got this idea. Nobody's doing this." And
I'm always like, "Well,
>> reason.
>> that Yeah, that means one of two things.
It means that, you know, like you're
just the smart guy that's the first one
to have this idea or there's a really
good reason why nobody's doing it. And
it's like turns out with drinkware,
there's some really good reasons why
making stainless steel and cited
drinkware in the United States is very
hard. Um so, at this point, most of what
we do is I would call it secondary
manufacturing. And this is uh I know
Shawn does some of this as well. This is
all of the kind of ornamentation layer
of our drinkware. We're laser engraving,
we're UV printing, we're uh heat
transfer, we're doing embroidery, uh and
all of that stuff really plays out well
with customization, chasing orders, and
different things. And so, we've we've
learned a lot there. A lot of highs, a
lot of lows, and I I I would liken
Here's Here's the analogy I get.
I would say building manufacturing is
like building a two-sided marketplace
that it really can add enterprise value
to your company if you're successful.
It's just really freaking hard to do,
and you're probably more likely to fail
um than you are to succeed in it. And
so, for us, I think on the uh Simple
Modern side, we haven't figured out how
to do it yet. Um but, the advances in
robotics and technology make it very
possible that it's something we look at
again.
And then we got into other things like
electrolyte powder and stuff where
vertically integrating would be
um would be more tenable. And I think
what we've learned over in that area is
that whether or not you do it, it's very
helpful in negotiating with suppliers.
If you have a credible threat that you
could do the thing, then it really
changes the type of prices that they
they offer you and the type of
automation that they're willing to do.
And it it kind of becomes their job to
price their product and their offering
in a way where it's just on the edge
where it's not worth it for you to
vertically integrate. And so that can be
really helpful as well.
>> Mike, in in the
insulated steel drinkware, out of my own
curiosity here,
what makes it hard to make in
the US? Is it labor? Is it materials?
Like is it all the inputs? Is it
>> Steel is a highly political
uh material.
So, in fact, even just this last week,
um there were some up updates to the 301
section of 301 stuff from the White
House.
Uh you do still have um
some significant steel industry in
America.
Um
I would say that China has been uh I
guilty of dumping. And so there have
been points where they just made a ton
and dumped it on the market.
>> [snorts]
>> And so
it's it they really do have access to
lower cost steel. That's a piece.
But the overriding thing that you learn
is that like we probably have, I don't
know, 10 major ingredients, we'll say,
like kind of uh
pieces or different things we need. We
need silicone, we need PP, we need
powder coating, we need steel, we need
and and then on top of that it's
probably a 30-step process to make these
things.
And so a really good example that we ran
across,
silicone, we use silicone in our stuff.
And it was like, well,
okay, we could buy it from China, don't
love that because we're doing a bunch of
colors and and still have this
dependency on China.
What if we made the silicone here? And
we we kind of pulled on that thread.
What we learned was even if we bought a
silicone injection machine and made the
silicone here, we couldn't make it even
even if you didn't include the cost of
machinery, we couldn't make it for what
China was selling it for.
And nobody really knows why that is. You
know, obviously there's some kind of
subsidization or something going on over
there. And this is this is kind of part
of the reason why China has become such
a juggernaut in manufacturing is that
they have all these cottage industries
and a lot of them are at prices that you
just really cannot replicate in the US.
And so one of the issues you have is
it's like, well, I don't know that a lot
of the cost saving isn't there. But then
there's this other issue going on which
is
um if you can get 80% of your stuff
reliably here, but 20% of it still has
to come from China and you still have
all of the dependencies, then how much
are you ahead by making 80% of it here?
So, it's complicated is is the short
answer and uh I think
there's a we're at a unique moment in
time. I'd love to talk about this as the
conversation goes on because I do think
we're at a unique moment in time with
what's going to happen with robotics
where some of this stuff could change.
But uh obviously China won this era of
manufacturing by and large, especially
in in kind of durables.
>> What's up, operators? Welcome to the
Rich Panel ad read. Rich Panel's been a
sponsor for over 12 months. I've been a
paying customer for over 12 months. And
guess what? I just renewed to pay again
for another year. We have cut our SAS
bill in half and automation dropped our
cost per ticket by 70%. Our CSAT has
also improved from 88%, which is still
really good, to 96%, best in class all
powered by Rich Panel. I told them last
year, "Hey, you guys need to do the same
thing with returns." And now Rich Panel
has a returns portal. It's built to cut
down your tickets and convert more
refunds into exchanges. They do the
heavy lifting, data import,
self-service, retention flows, team
training, all of it, and they'll be live
in 2 weeks. If you want to save 30%
guaranteed on help desk and now returns,
book a demo.
>> There is something called China math.
And I saw Matt, your eyes just like go,
"What? How can we do everything
like this and they can still beat us on
price? There is something weird, and you
can call it subsidization, you can call
it whatever you want, but it's expensive
to have labor in China.
It's expensive to ship things into
China. It's expensive. I'm really lean,
and some things they can just make
astronomically cheaper than we are. And
I'm like, "How can you possibly do
that?" And I don't know, but I would say
this, there are such
problems in manufacturing in the United
States. And part of it is our attitude,
I believe, that you set something up and
then you manufacture. And theirs is they
make all their money on manufacturing,
right? They're going to make it, and
they got to have a margin. Somehow they
got to make some money. So, they're
always trying to get better, penny by
penny, penny, dollar by dollar. In US,
we set up manufacturing, we're like,
"Yeah, that's pretty good. Like, we can
make that thing for 20 bucks. Let's kick
that in for a couple years." I heard
Mike on the Operators Podcast one time
say about every year he goes back to
China, they have new machines doing new
processes, making it more efficient. Is
that right, Mike?
>> Yeah, the uh I'm I'm going to pull up
this stat, uh but if you look at
robotics installed worldwide, it's
fairly shocking, because uh China I
think that the perception for a long
time is that China and some of these
developing economies, what they did is
they threw people at the problem. And
and maybe that was true for an era, but
what's true today with China is that
they're throwing robotics at the
problem. And so, what what is kind of a
narrative violation and also should give
people should wake people up is that
China is installing robotics. I I I pull
the stat, but I believe they installed
about as much robotics as the rest of
the world combined
last year. And so they clearly have a
vision for the future and that it's
going to be robotics driven. So early
on, there's a great book we've
referenced on here before, go and buy it
if you haven't read it called Apple in
China. And it talks about how Apple as a
company helped China to develop into the
manufacturing superpower because they
certainly weren't when Apple started
making things there.
Um but the thing that I think
you can't Listen, game recognizes game.
And China didn't have a great hand 30
years ago and they have maximized that
hand. And even if our countries are
somewhat adversarial and there's some
ways that they do things that I don't
agree with, as an operator, I look at it
and I'm like, it's pretty amazing. Like
you were basically all you had was cheap
labor to throw at things and you have
worked your way up the value stack.
And so like yes, like when I go over
there,
what I see is almost fully automated
production at this point. And and it's
impressive. And I think that my my
personal view on the technology side is
what makes this moment in AI so
interesting is not the software. If
you're I mean if you're in consumer
goods and you think the most interesting
thing about AI is the software and the
ad creation, I disagree. I think the
most exciting idea is that when the
robotics and the AI come together, like
fulfillment is going to totally change.
Manufacturing's going to totally change.
Product development's going to totally
change. And and my sense is we're
probably a year or two out from that.
And and there's going to be fortunes
made.
>> And the beginning of the change is like
within the next 24 months.
>> Yeah, you look at like Brett Adcock and
some of the the videos he's posting, you
know,
just the robotics is clearly getting
really really good. And then imagine
dropping the latest version of Claude,
the latest version of
chat GPT inside of it where it's
basically like a genius and it has
access to the physical world and then
you're like, "Okay, now I'm going to
turn you loose in figuring out the most
efficient way to make this bottle and
you can go through a million
iterations." And it's like, "Oh, yeah,
like that's believable." And I think
that that's where we're headed in short
order.
>> I think though like and I've listened to
Curtis talk about this with with Port
man whether that
if you're going to get into
manufacturing, you need to get
comfortable getting really into it. And
that is you also need to understand all
of the inputs. You have to be
comfortable going very deep in the
supply chain.
Um because there is a fragility to it.
Which might just called out. Like
we know
every input in our business
uh and we build direct relationships
with all those people and we're looking
for secondary and third backups. Like
we're it making things isn't just a like
I'm going to buy some machines and I'm
going to do the finished good. If you're
going to do it, I think you kind of have
to look at like how China how does China
do this so well? The one thing
that I would caution people on
is
the political and monetary system that
China has. Like they are fully aligned
as a nation.
And that's where this whole idea of like
subsidizing even it it's like don't take
that literally. That word is not a
literal word.
It's that like the entire system is
built to support
this set of objectives. And it's a it's
it's dictated. It's like, "No,
manufacturing's important. Everything
will be set up for you. Like the banks
will be friendlier, the labor will be
cheap. We'll provide everything. We'll
give you cheaper real estate, cheaper
power. Uh we will just like set the
whole system up to allow you to succeed
in this one thing.
And in the USA, it's a free market. The
whole system doesn't give a [__]
It is like chasing the most efficient
turning of a dollar.
Right?
And that may not mean that it's good to
make things here. You know, I I I often
think that uh I'm I'm proud of our
manufacturing. Like there's nothing I
like doing better than bringing people
in and what you see behind me is a very
small portion of it. It is enormous,
right? So, I bring them into one little
door and then you go and you go to
bigger and bigger. It's like Willy
Wonka. People love it, right? And I'm so
proud of it.
But it's a pain in the ass. It really
really is.
And I think we can match China with what
we do in our manufacturing in terms of
price. But China will not get beat.
They will actually go out and now
they're using Bangladesh and Cambodia
and other labor because their labor is
higher and here's the materials and
here's our sourcing and they thought
that well, now they need to beat us. So,
they go out and they own the factories
in these other countries where they're
paying a couple hundred dollars a month
for labor rather than what we pay, which
is a lot lot more, right? So, they're
they they live and die on manufacturing.
They've got to make it work. So, they're
going to figure out a way years in
advance to put the time and the money in
order to do that. And I don't think of
China as adversarial uh although I it
is. I I understand that. Uh
but they're all into manufacturing. I'm
in Leon, Mexico.
And if you want to know manufacturing
gone wrong,
they've been doing it for 50 years. And
what they do here is they work with the
United States. And somebody from the
United States comes in says, "Will you
make our product for us?" And they say,
"Yes, we will."
And all of a sudden
they they're building it up, they're
building it up, and then demand goes
down in the US and they stop buying.
And what happens is that business goes
out of business.
Like they they just get killed. Uh
there's a company I'll just say it out
loud, Frye Boots. Frye Boots is a
100-year-old company, right? They have
twice went bankrupt here and take
millions of dollars from the people down
here. Just crushed. And then they come
back 3 months later and said, "Hey,
guess what? We sold to somebody else.
We're still Frye Boots, but now we want
you to make again. We're not going to
pay you back the $4 million that we owe
you, right?" So, the manufacturing here
doesn't have the support of the
government. They don't have all of these
windfalls. They're just people trying to
make things. They're not as good and
they're not efficient. So, I had to come
in with my
entrepreneur mindset and say, "How do I
stabilize this manufacturing so that I
have the right product to sell at the
right time?" Cuz as a as an entrepreneur
and a marketing guy, that's all I care.
Give me the right product at the right
price at the right time.
>> Longtime sponsor Northbeam is launching
incrementality later this quarter. This
means that you can now have the trifecta
of marketing measurement all in one
platform. That is multi-touch
attribution, media mix modeling, and
incrementality holdouts all inside of
Northbeam. You can automate that lift
testing end-to-end, unify results with
your MTA and your MMM. This is a lot of
letters, but if you know, you know. And
you can start to cut what doesn't work,
and you can scale what works. You can do
this all with confidence. This is why
this is such an incredible add to
Northbeam. Northbeam's incrementality
measures what results marketing is
actually generating, not just what
they're claiming credit for. As a CEO,
that's like music to my ears. Sign up
now and you can lock in 50% off
unlimited tests for the year.
>> Well, and that's I would love to hear
it, Curtis. Like cuz I I think you're
underselling
just how dramatically you've been able
to use vertical integration to create
enterprise value. Like I think I think
you're an example where you're the the
value of your company is just
significantly higher because of your
vertical integration than it would be
otherwise. And I'd love you to talk
about that. You know, I know I'm asking
you to kind of brag on your own company,
but like because of your cost structure,
my understanding is you have an
unbelievable value proposition that
leads to a cult-like following. So, can
you just share some of how becoming
vertically integrated has made your
brand such a powerhouse?
>> Uh I think I can talk about myself. I
usually don't. Thank you so much, buddy.
I appreciate that.
>> Oh, challenge accepted, Mike. Challenge
accepted.
>> How dumb I am is I had my own
manufacturing before I knew the word
vertically integrated. Right? Like I had
no idea. I started making in a garage.
So, then we moved to manufacturing in
Portland. And it was just like I need
product to sell this weekend. I need it
today. I need it right now. When we came
to Leon, we were blown away at what was
going on. We
I knew problems were coming in 2018-19
in somewhere in the supply chain. I knew
we were growing so fast I had to break
free, but I didn't know what it was. So,
I spent a lot of time in Leon setting up
the potential for manufacturing. And all
of a sudden, COVID hit, right?
And we had just started setting up the
foundations. So, we got 8,000 square
meters, 10,000 square foot, just a
little little place, 10,000 square foot,
five machines in the corner. And we just
started to build and build and built.
And now as somebody and and I know we're
talking on Operator's Podcast to people
who do a million to 10 million. And
they're like, well, I need to make a
decision of what I do here. I didn't
make a decision. The decisions made me
go all in and say, if I want to win this
game, how do I do this? And I'm going to
make manufacturing the right decision. I
didn't start manufacturing and question
it every week. Like, does that make
sense? I don't like say, "Oh, maybe I
shouldn't have done this." I say, "How
can I beat people?" And we go in. So, we
got the materials. I have 5 million
square feet of leather in my facilities
right here. 5 million square feet.
That's a crazy amount. And the reason I
have that is I learned that it doesn't
matter
if I can make a product fast. I have to
make the right product in the right
leather and the right color, right? So,
I can't just paint it like you do on on
a mug, right? You You have to actually
have that leather.
I became where I was able to take my
marketing in the United States, Mike.
And they became this pull system.
They're just always saying, "More. More
of this. More of this." And I found
myself spending 80 90% of my time in
Mexico
feeding the beast of marketing, right?
Like, they just want that product. And
the numbers cycle on everybody.
We have a product right now that we
projected we would sell 100,000 of that
bag for this year, right? And after
January, it was we were going to sell
about 100,000 of that bag. And after
February, we were going to sell 100,000
of that bag. We did a Tik Tok. We
started doing $100,000
a day on Tik Tok.
And guess what? They all sold the same
bag. Now we're projected to sell 500,000
of that bag.
>> That's the advantage, Mike. That's the
enterprise value. It's that Curtis
Curtis can follow the consumer demand.
And in in a traditional supply chain,
you were trying to predict it. So, like,
Mike, in your case,
uh Simple Modern has
long lead time abilities to project
volumes because you're working with
Target and Amazon and they're buying.
And they're like you're probably
planning out I mean I'm going to guess
like 12 months, something like that,
right?
Whereas in D2C the reason that
owned manufacturing can be valuable is
what Curtis is saying. Where it's like I
you never really know what the consumer
is going to want one month to the next.
The Oscars can show up and completely
change
fashion.
The the somebody could drop like one of
the Kardashians can say this color is
the new color.
And if you there's no way you knew that
was coming. Like Curtis wouldn't know
that all of a sudden his most popular
color bag is because you know Kim
decided that gray
is going to be 2026's color. Like that's
the issue with a lot of categories.
That's the same issue that Pela has.
We're trend followers.
I'm not so big that I make them.
Right? And the the preferences are where
the demand is. And and then funny
enough, that's how algorithms work. Like
what Curtis is describing, this is why
like it's so smart that you do this
Curtis. It's like Meta and TikTok are
just going to satisfy what the consumer
wants. That's just AI. If we've all used
these chats, like they're really good at
telling us that we're awesome. So like
these AI things are just going to say
straight up like this is what's popular.
How do I serve more to it? Curtis, you
can just supply it. And a traditional
supply chain could not.
They'd be four months waiting.
>> Well, I was just going to make one
distinction which I think is important
which is
that whether or not you use molds in
your business is a big deal
for two reasons. One is that
80-90% of the world the world's molds
are made in China.
And so like if you need tooling, you're
going to have to go through China and
tooling just takes a while. It's just
like a multi-month process to get a good
tool made and functioning properly. So
Curtis can stockpile leather
and then be like, "Hey, I can have that
leather sewn differently next Tuesday if
I want to." I mean, we have to design
it, but he has more flexibility, whereas
with me,
if I want to change a lid, it's like,
well, it's 3 to 4 months minimum, you
know, and it's like, I've got to get a
tool made and then I've got to ship it,
you know, from China to here.
And so, that was one of the things that
we ran into is that if you have a
business that requires molds to make a
thing, then it has to be a product
that's just not changing at all. You
can't be It's really the opposite of
what you're saying, Matt, which is you
can't be trend trend-based at all. And
unfortunately, hydration is more
trend-based because if there's any
amount of changes, then it kind of cooks
you uh when you're using molds. Now,
when you're doing uh I think
consumables, when you're that that have
ingredients that can be mixed
differently, and when you have soft
goods, um I think that there's more
opportunity to do exactly what you're
saying and fast-following. And that's
another way you can unlock value. I I
think what we're getting to is that
there's several different ways you can
unlock value here, and one of them is
that you make your business more
valuable by de-risking having all this
exposure to other governments and other
countries. One way is that you can
unlock better um economics potentially
by being vertically integrated. Um one
of them is that you can fast-follow
demand more quickly and stay in stock
when other people can't. But the the
main thing I'd want people to hear from
me is that
I think making good decisions here is
highly contingent on understanding your
product category. And that was probably
where I misstepped is that I was I
didn't understand that my category was
still moving around so much that it was
going to be hard to be like, "We're just
going to make a a gazillion of this one
thing." And it's like, well, if the
market doesn't move at all, that would
work great, but it did. And so, it was
not as effective as I'd hoped.
>> The I mean, Curtis, I don't know if
you've done this, but like 5 million
square feet is 87 football fields.
Yeah.
>> Right? It's like it's almost the size of
the Pentagon.
Yeah, do it height by height by like how
much that is. No, it's if if you
actually I what we use in leather in a
year, I figured it out with AI one time.
If you take a semi-truck full of leather
and take the entire truck and turn it up
like this, it would be like 56 Empire
States tall of trucks full of leather.
Like it's literally crazy amounts of
leather, right? So, it is a commodity
that we use and it's something that gets
thrown away. I want everyone to know
that. Like this leather gets thrown away
if you don't make it into something.
Now, the one thing I do want to cuz I
love the thing the reason I was a big
fan of the Operator's podcast before I
ever started coming on here and I'd
watch it. And I'm looking for those one
or two things that really really help
me. And the one thing I want to tell
everybody watching is
I did not start manufacturing think I
was going to build this.
I wanted product for three or six months
in the future and I wanted to solidify.
I was making quarterly and yearly
decisions, not five and 10-year
decisions, right? There's no way that I
I did this. The neat thing is in Mexico,
it's very modular like Legos. You
actually have a warehouse and when
you're done with that one, you knock a
hole in the wall and you have a
warehouse next door and then the next
one and you just build on as you're
building. So, we started as a small one
and then you just start knocking out
walls and building and creating
something bigger. Because I don't want
anyone to think I have to decide do I go
to China or do I manufacture
>> build a million square feet and do it
here?
>> I Curtis, I could not agree more and I
think very practically, if you're going
to take on manufacturing, you should
absolutely
try and view it like starting a
business. How do I break this down into
atomic components to the maximum extent
possible and how do I try and prove out
positive unit economics with the minimum
amount of investment possible. And like
it's
especially in our case the fact that we
had capital worked against us cuz it's
like we can go and buy $5 worth of
equipment and this kind of grand opening
of this huge facility. We should have
never done that. It should have been
like how do we invest $100,000
and prove out a piece of the concept and
then if that works we go to $200,000 and
that we just incrementally build on top
of that.
>> That's what we did.
>> Yeah, it's like this is just how good
operators think.
>> Yeah, we bought we bought like a used
injection molding machine.
>> Yes.
>> You know.
>> Exactly.
>> It was like 90 grand.
>> It should be like as another example we
were like well we don't want to have
dependency on China so we bought an Aoki
which is this like kind of Rolls-Royce
injection machine, this huge injection
machine but they're three times more
expensive than China and we bought
something new. So we bought the
Rolls-Royce that's three times more
expensive
than the Chinese version and we bought
it new. If we had bought a used Chinese
version we literally could have gotten
it for 10% of the price. And if I could
go back I would first I would shake
myself but then
I would be like listen, you know, like
start small, prove it out and then as
you prove it out continue to lean in
with capital and so that would be my my
argument for anybody considering this is
like you should try it but just make
yourself prove out the concept along the
way because the way you really get in a
trouble here is where you commit to a
big facility and then you realize one
year into the lease uh-oh we don't need
all this space. You buy a million dollar
machine and you realize uh-oh this isn't
the machine we needed and there's not
really a great resale market or
whatever. It's these kind of mistakes.
If you're scaling an e-commerce brand
today, ads alone aren't enough.
AfterSell focuses on the one moment that
every brand already owns, after
checkout, and turns the post-purchase
moment into more profit. Monetize every
order with post-purchase offers and
thank you page experiences without
disrupting checkout or hurting
conversion. Enterprise grade tech used
by Gap, Ticketmaster, Macy's, and Target
now driving results for brands like True
Classic, Hex Clad, Ridge, and Jones
Road. I would know. This is the reason I
ended up buying three pants from Hex
Clad instead of two. AfterSell has
already generated over 1 billion in
additional revenue for e-commerce
brands. Revenue that doesn't require
more traffic or higher CAC. So, check
out AfterSell and tell them that the
operator sent you.
>> So, I got a couple points. I I think
Mike, you started off by saying
going vertical is like standing up a
double-sided marketplace, which are, for
people who love business, some of the
hardest companies to build. Is when you
have to build a marketplace. So
difficult cuz you're standing up two
types of demand.
For I would caution,
not even caution, I would say that if
you're going to go out and go vertical,
you shouldn't do it purely on the I
think I can make it cheaper. So, I think
I can get more margin for myself than I
get from a third-party manufacturer.
I really strongly believe that you
should be doing it for like other
strategic reasons that are going to
increase enterprise value. So, like in
my case, what I've said before, I think
on this show is
it's the money was going to get spent
anyway. So, I was either going to buy
inventory or I was going to build a
factory. Now, by building factories, you
pull the money forward, so you need to
finance that, right? We went to outside
investors to do that.
But, we the reason we did this was now
we are
uh much more cash
uh what do you it like cash cycle
efficient. So like we're a negative
working capital consumer business. When
I sell things, I make them. I don't buy
them and then hope to sell them.
So for us that was like that's a good
reason to do it.
You know, I make them and I traded
margin. That's the fun part. We are
still about 20% 30% more expensive than
if I just bought the crap from China.
But I'm negative working capital. That
is worth the margin.
And it's no different than if somebody
was to tell you and this is common
advice in consumer
be willing to trade margin for better
payment terms.
That's the same advice.
Right? I just we set up our own we're
basically our own bank. Like we set up
our own payment terms.
>> That was excellent clarity there. That
I'm going to I always like to tell
people how smart our manufacturing is.
I'm going to tell you how dumb it is
right now, right? Because it takes me
the marketing mind of our company
to 90% of my time is spent on making the
product.
I I always like to talk about how smart
manufacturing is once you get it set up
and it is really hard but it is also
really really dumb. What we're finding
out right now, I found out yesterday is
that yes, we're kind of even par in
making with China. You said it's a
little bit more
uh that when you're making but now China
is going into Cambodia and they're
coming back and saying hey we can make
we can take your material from Brazil
air ship it into Cambodia, make it, pay
the tariffs, put it on a boat, and take
it to Dallas cheaper than you can make
it right there and put it in a truck for
a few hours and send it into Dallas. So
you're like well, that's good but you
need both. That might be good for long
term but I need products next week.
Uh as I was mentioning we had a product
that recently took off. If I I that in a
traditional thing, I would go give them
the
uh
the specs, they would make samples, we
would approve, put a PO, we would send
materials, and I would get that product
in October.
Last week was Semana Santa, which was
Holy Week. Everyone has the week off.
We had people volunteer and say,
"Anybody want to work for the week?" And
they came in and made that specific
product, and we produced 12,000 of those
bags last week that were on a truck
within a week to Dallas to make sure
that that flow was good. So, there's
good and bad that go.
I wish I didn't have the manufacturing.
I'm going to tell you this, I I I love
it, but if I could just sit back in the
United States and have people order the
things and it would work as well, I
would do it. I just don't think it would
work as well.
>> Have you ever thought of splitting the
company, Curtis? So, like owning a
manufacturing company that is in service
to Portland Leather Goods, but is also
in service to other companies?
So, you build up the B2B sort of like
this stable base of
of like capacity cuz that's the
double-sided marketplace part that's so
hard of this is like because you're in
charge of your own demand.
>> Yeah.
>> There's a but there's a big problem with
it, Matt, and once you've run it, you
get the problem.
You want Curtis's manufacturing has to
be captive to Portland Leather Goods.
Because
it is
incredibly detrimental if he says and
actually I'm just going to zoom out. I'm
going to I'm going to give a bigger
concept we haven't hit on yet.
Here's how manufacturing works,
consistent significant volume. If you
know that you can get consistent
significant, especially predictable
volume, then you can make manufacturing
work. What is the problem? That is
actually really hard to deliver on. That
volume is lumpy and what people want
changes and it is very difficult. Your
people are hourly and they want you to
say, "Hey, uh show up for 40 hours a
week." But, your demand profile is
almost never like you have to bust your
butt to try and smooth out your demand
profile where it can line up with your
people and your production. And so, what
you just said is the kind of siren call
of like, "Well,
what if we split this company out
and we would have we brought on other
customers, then we'd have more volume
and we wouldn't have weeks where we have
nothing to work on or whatever, and we
could kind of smooth it out." But, the
problem with that
is that none of this makes any sense if
Curtis's manufacturing when he needs
them to do something if they can't do
it. And when you start to get other
clients, you start to get these
bottlenecks where there's a week where
everybody needs something. And you've
got to choose. And like you absolutely
have to choose Port- Portland Leather
Goods. And so, then if you're another
person buying from his manufacturing,
it's like, "Well, I know I'm going to
get big boyed at any point if Curtis
needs something, right?" And so, this is
probably not the best solution for me
for my manufacturing. And this is
anyway, it all goes back to and you you
mentioned balance sheets, Matt. But,
ironically,
one of the places where you can get the
worst balance sheets is when you own
manufacturing because the factory has to
run. If the factory isn't running, I
mean, you're paying rent, you're paying
your your paying on notes on these
machines, you're paying people's
salaries. You can't just furlough
people. And so,
you get this temptation to make product
even when you don't know where it's
going. And that's exactly how you
absolutely burden your balance sheet
with a bunch of inventory that you don't
know where it's going.
>> Mike, you're so smart. I I used to say
that in such a great way. I would say it
in a a much more simplistic way.
I've always been blessed to have people
in my life who are kind of messed up.
And so they do things so dumb, you say,
I don't want to do something that dumb.
Right? Like I'm a long-term recovering
alcoholic. So if you're around a lot of
alcoholics and mess up their lives,
you're like, well, if I just don't do
what Jim does, I'll be better off.
[laughter]
I live in Leon, Mexico. They're a
manufacturing, and you watch these
people struggle. They find somebody, oh,
you want us to make this product? Great.
You spend all the time in courting them,
making samples, developing, starting a
run. You make a few of these things, and
they're like, yeah, that didn't work.
Let's try something else. You're like,
well, all my cost was up front. Like I
just want a manufacturing line to run.
Somebody told me one time, if you want
to see how efficient your manufacturing
is, look out at those machines and that
needle needs to be moving up and down at
all times. That means you have the right
materials at the right time feeding
those lines. If you're always changing
products out for somebody else, you're
always slowing the process down. There
are some lines that I have, probably
maybe 20 of my lines never change
product. They're making the same product
just in a different color all year long.
That's pure efficiency. You can't get
that if you sub it out to somebody else.
I also know a lot of American companies
are really bad at stretching you out and
then getting in financial difficulty and
not paying you, and you get stuck with
their materials and the losses. And then
when you have to lay people off, it's
Mexico, you have to pay their for
months. You have a lot of money that you
have to pay. You have your fixed costs.
You Matt, we've all thought of it.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah, I'm asking because everybody
thinks about it. That's it's it's
totally Mike nailed it. It's the siren
call of of manufacture. I would the I
guess the caveat here would be in
consumer manufacturing, right? So like
if you're and I think Mike, what you're
calling out is the which business is the
priority at that point. So like if
Portland Leather Goods is the brand is
always the priority because that's where
you feel the most enterprise value is.
Of course,
the the capacity of the factory business
needs to be subservient to PLG.
And if it's the flip, then it's just
being okay that like the consumer brand
like I do know there's a
I think
there is a t-shirt brand or like a
basics brand in Canada or in the US
where they actually own their own loom.
Like they are the the actual
manufacturer.
But they were the
manufacturing business first and the
brand came second. And sometimes I go to
buy a damn t-shirt and they're freaking
sold out.
And I'm like and I know what's happening
behind the scenes. It's like, yeah, they
just their their their manufacturing
customers took all the freaking
material. Like that's what it is. And
the consumer brand
is just left sitting there saying, "Hey,
we're sold out for now."
>> Implementing AI without trusted data is
shooting in the dark and building out a
foundation from scratch, dealing with
Tableau, dealing with data pipelines,
dealing with all that, it doesn't have
to be your headache. You can hire Saras
Analytics to handle that stuff for you.
Saras IQ gives your leadership team a
single shared view of the truth.
Contribution margin, channel
performance, customer economics, all can
be answered instantly with the power of
Saras Analytics. Do not fall behind.
Saras Analytics is experts, they've set
it up for Ridge, Huckberry, and hundreds
of other brands. Speak to them today.
Connect whatever AI tool you already use
and you can put that right on top of
your personal data privately, securely,
and you can start talking to your data
like your favorite chatbot.
>> I have two observations I just want to
make and one is
there's a reason why China has all the
manufacturing and that's because it's
generally thought of as a crappy
industry, right? And I think one of
points we're kind of making here is that
it is a crappy industry to be in unless
you have some way to make it less crappy
and by and vertically integrating is one
of those ways. Um and there's a there's
even some things we haven't mentioned
like hey if you have kind of proprietary
processes and you don't want those
leaked out to all your competitors or
whatever like keeping it in house but
all that to say manufacturing not sexy
not fun not good margins
real competitive lots of ways to go
bankrupt. You should only do it if
you're able to layer on value in some
kind of a way that makes it better and
makes it more attractive from an
economic perspective. Now one of the few
ways that you can kind of consolidate
things where it does make it more likely
to work and more value accretive is by
adding some of the operational things
like fulfillment and logistics and we
have definitely seen that what
even though we failed in many of our
vertical integration with manufacturing
it pushed us to develop a lot of
capabilities around warehousing and
around fulfillment that have been great
for us. Like a really simple for us is
that we were making things for Walmart
in our facility.
And so we started fulfilling all of our
stuff from Walmart from our facility
instead of somewhere else and then as we
were doing that Walmart's like hey you
know I don't know if you guys want to do
this but we actually have this pallet
program where we don't send you a PO
where you have to go pick everything but
literally we'll just come pick up
pallets from you. And it was wildly more
efficient. It was like you know Walmart
could send us a huge PO a huge PO and
one person could pick it in three hours
or some kind of crazy because they're
literally just going in and grabbing
pallets with a pallet jack
and tremendous savings there. And so
if you're going to really think about
this you had better have some kind of a
justification around why you want to be
a manufacturing and it has to be around
the way to bundle a bunch of services
together or to create some kind of
unique proprietary value because of the
the you own. Otherwise I don't think
you're going to like the experience very
much.
Wow. You know,
I'm a bootstrap guy. I I always brag
about it. I talk about it. That's just
who I am. I don't want to give up that
control. Mike, you had to go out and get
investors to build this up.
No, I I lit my own money on fire,
Curtis. I'm staring at my computer at
Matt and I said, Mike,
>> Okay.
>> So, I had my alliteration right and the
the name wrong.
>> even know which is worse, Curtis,
burning my money or somebody else's
money.
>> They're both They're both [laughter]
suck, but I I set my own money on fire
on this particular case.
>> No, I set investors' money on fire.
Uh
Yeah, no, look, the
this was sort of one of those rare
examples where I do think consumer has
business with outside capital.
Like, I'm sort of in camp 99% of the
time you should probably bootstrap in
consumer. Like, your your life will be
better.
Um
It building factories, like large CAPEX,
that kind of stuff, that is where
investors can be very, very helpful.
Right? So, that's kind of why we started
down that path and then ultimately we
raised more money for Lomi because of
the R&D piece, but that's that's a
that's a whole other game, right? Like,
real R&D costs real dollars. Um you
know, Pela R&D is like tooling. You
know, what do we what are we cutting
steel on? And which is a whole other set
of challenges. Like, I I when Mike is
talking about tooling in China, man,
like God, do I feel that pain. I have
I have three sets of 64 tools
right now
uh at $6,000 a piece or $8,000 a piece.
So, like, and and they weigh like 1,000
lb each.
You know, so you got to move these damn
things around inside these facilities. I
think Mike is just like you the the
point you're making on manufacturing
around like you need to see it through
this lens of
a bundle of
services or value like a value add
wrapper
and that that's the justification for
doing it. And I again I want to like
emphasize in consumer like I have a my
I'm my family is in aluminum extrusion.
It has been for almost 50 years.
Uh great freaking business. Massive
contracts are decades long.
Like the world needs steel, lots of it.
So, that's an awesome manufacturing
business. It's in Italy. They've been
doing it forever. Great great business
to be in. Now, it's a commodity
business. There's downsides to it, but
that's all B2B and I think just like B2B
SaaS that's a different animal. So, I
think like put all that aside and just
like this is consumer.
I would love to hear uh Mike
you talk a bit more on the fulfillment
the like warehouse running part because
I think like we've been talking about
like Curtis is I'm staring at this like
giant leather factory. Then the the the
next level up is like should you run
your own warehouse?
Yeah. You know, we know a lot of people
that run their own warehouse.
>> Look at the videos that get posted on or
on Twitter, you know? I It's funny. I
will never call it X. I don't I just
don't even think it can be
It's like I've I'm I'm making myself
more of an uh uncle in everybody's eyes
like the longer I call it Twitter, but I
don't care.
But like if you look at all the videos,
the example videos that people are
putting out of these robots, they're
like folding laundry, putting dishes
away, or sorting packages. You know,
it's like always like one of these like
three or four use cases and it's like
Yeah, exactly. Or or you know, preparing
for judgment day. But it's like
it doesn't take you being particularly
uh
I don't know intuitive to understand
that one of the places we're going is
people are going to do 0% of pick and
pack, you know, for most of these
companies. Like that is just all going
to go robotic. And and in some ways
my view would be if you want to take on
vertical integration, vertical
integration around your uh inventory
storage and your fulfillment is maybe
one of the easiest things to do right
off the bat. Because if you are doing
your own storage, you are going to be
way better than market rates.
And that fulfillment uh
I mean, if you're doing your own
fulfillment, you're going to be better
than what the market's offering you. But
also,
you can start to look at your first
CapEx expenditure. And I I think it's
it's kind of breaking the seal on your
first successful CapEx expenditure is
kind of like what we're talking about.
And so, like I it's it it doesn't take
much imagination to say
if you have a building and you're doing,
you know, your fulfillment of 1,000 or
500 or whatever orders a day, then,
okay, if a robot if an Optimus robot
costs me $40,000,
how many fulfillments does it have to do
to pay itself off? And you start doing
the math and you're like, these things
can pay themselves off in 6 months.
And just just to take a step back,
in some ways, cuz we've talked about
this idea of LTV to CAC before,
I think you want to think about
equipment the same way. It's like the
quicker you pay it off, the better it
is. The end, right? And the longer that
payback period is, the more likely you
are to someday very much regret that you
made that purchase. Just like the longer
you go out to pay back your customer
acquisition cost, like the more likely
it is that you never pay it back. And
so, if these robots are $40,000,
then how long, how many activities would
it take you or like like a really simple
thing is if you can save $1.50 in pick
pack fees per order,
okay, it only takes you about 27,000
orders to pay off a robot. And you can
just kind of do the math and then you're
like, wait a second, I can pay a robot
off in 6 months, in 9 months, and then
I've got a fully paid off robot, and who
knows what I can do with this thing. And
so, like, my my sense
is that that is where we're going to go.
It's interesting because Calcanas went
and toured the Optimus facility,
and the one of crazier things he said is
he's like, people are going to forget
that Tesla ever made cars. Now, that is
a crazy thing to say as somebody who
owns a Tesla, but it is at least
semi-plausible that robots become so
ubiquitous that they are the next iPhone
product, and this would be one of the
use cases that's just like right off the
bat doing
>> so are you pro own your own fulfillment,
then? Like, I guess if you're looking
into the future, cuz it was always at
the counter to this
uh the whole 3PL versus own fulfillment
was always when you grow, what do you
do?
>> with 3PLs is that um and the reason why
most people use 3PLs is the reason why
most people use contract manufacturing.
It's the same business in disguise. It's
like, you have to have a somewhat steady
flow and predictability, or it doesn't
work. If I think I need 10,000 sq ft of
space, and I actually need 20,000, then
I have a problem. Or if I commit myself
to 10,000 sq ft of space, and then I
actually only have 3,000 sq ft worth of
product, then I've got a bunch of dead
stuff that I'm paying for. And the same
thing, if I've got hourly employees who
their job is to come in and pick and
pack orders, and today I have 100
orders, but tomorrow I might have 1,000,
well, I'm I'm going to have a problem.
And so, it's it's the same kind of like,
if you have consistency, I mean, you you
mentioned your family and aluminum.
There's a reason these contracts are
multi-decade. It's because they have to
be, so that you can work it out. And so,
I I guess what I'm saying is I think
what people are going to find is it's
cuz we have a lot of, you know, 3PLs in
America. I I think people are going to
find it's much easier for me to kind of
bite off that piece of the physical
world, the manufacturing as a first
step. And I think the robotics is going
to make that even easier. And so,
uh again, this is not sexy stuff. Like,
you're not generating massive amounts of
EV here. But, the once you have it,
there are certain things that you can
do. Like,
>> Uh there's there's definitely defensive
There's like defensive maneuvers in some
having some of this stuff, right? I I do
listening to you guys talk, like I think
that
if I was going to guide
uh the listeners in this,
your level one move would be to go from
like 3PL to owned fulfillment,
right? Like, there's and there if
there's real advantages to it. Level two
would be uh I'm going to personalize, so
I'm going to do like printing,
embroidery, engraving, like that kind of
thing. Like, I we call it like light
assembly, light manufacturing. And the
level four would be
I'm going to Curtis it, and we're going
to do like cut and sew, we're going to
do cutting, we're going to like we're
actually going to manufacture, we're
going to build tools, like do what I do,
too.
Um and the level five above that would
be like even more vertical. So, like
Curtis is buying and storing massive
amounts of leather.
Um I I I I guess like maybe at some
point he could raise cows. But, like
there's at some point you got to stop
with the
like how deep you go in this because it
gets less sexy and there's less
enterprise value
the further you go.
>> Well, for the people just starting out,
uh
you know, we doubled every year. We went
literally made our goals in here, 1 2 4
8 16 32 64. And what I used to tell
people is it's not intuitive that every
year you're making as much that year as
you did in the entire history of your
company. So, when you're making eight,
you did what you did at one, two, and
four, right? When you're at 16, you did
what you did. So, every year you're
making the entire
compound of what you've done to that
point. So, when you're looking at a 3PL,
but we want to do our own fulfillment.
Yeah. And we're like, "Okay, how big of
a building do we get?"
Well, takes 6 months to get in. We're
going to be here this year, but next
year we're going to be again and at this
Well, are we going to get a building 16
times bigger than what we actually want
so we're fine in 3 years? Like, the
reason we never went 3PL was because I
didn't know how much space to get, how
many racks to buy, and I didn't want to
screw it up. So, I went safe. Now,
should we have? I think we should have.
And I'll tell you why. We just switched
3PLs. And I get a lot of questions about
3PLs from people. We started one 3PL.
They didn't know what they were doing
and they didn't care. And they were like
the worst 3PL you could have. So, we
moved to somebody who cared, who still
didn't know what they were doing. We
recently got an offer to save us $8
million a year by moving to another 3PL.
8 million. Guaranteed 8 million. And I'm
like, well, I like that. And I went to
my old people like, "Oh, no, no, we'll
just give you better prices. We'll save
you the 8 mil." I'm like, "You were
making 8 million in on me? You gave me
that bad a service? You were fighting
over a $50,000 charge that was your
fault and you could have You're making
more than 8 million on me? You jerks. Of
course, I have to leave right now,
right?" So, there's a lot of money in
that efficiency in what you're doing.
That I thought it was brilliant. That's
what Mike does. If you can value add in
something by having your own 3PL, I
think that's great. I like to go into
marketing is where your money's at,
right? Can I sell more at a cheaper
price? So, we're marketing company. So,
manufacturing is here and I'm like,
well, where can my time be best spent?
Like, if you learn how to sell, you're
just going to be better off.
We are in manufacturing heaven down here
in Leon. When I came down, I was told
that there were
400 tanneries and 800 uh shoemaking
factories in Leon. 800.
I've had at least a hundred of them come
to me and say, "Hey, we can make this
stuff. Do you want to set up a brand and
we'll sell your this stuff in the United
States." And you want to know what I
say? Marketing's the hard part. Running
a big manufacturing, as hard as it is,
it's not as important as knowing how to
create a brand and selling it to people.
>> Every SaaS company says they are
AI-powered, but very few can explain
what it actually does for the revenue of
my brand. This is why Postscript's
approach stood out to us. They don't
just build AI for demos or buzzwords,
they build it to drive real incremental
revenue. Postscript's AI called Shopper,
it shows up inside of SMS at moments
with real buyer intent, when shoppers
are likely asking questions, hesitating,
maybe even about to drop off. Shopper
can answer product questions instantly,
answer questions about fit,
availability, recommendations, order
issues, the kinds of stuff that people
usually bounce for. This means more
conversions, higher AOV, less lost
demand, so you are driving more revenue
and doing it more efficiently. Check out
Shopper from Postscript. We use it at
Pillow, which is why I am telling you to
check it out.
>> Why why is uh Bezos
going out and doing like what is he
doing? 100 billion or 200 billion, some
stupid number
that he's looking to put together to buy
or build manufacturing
capabilities.
>> I know nothing about that, Mike.
>> It just it it just seems like that all
the talking heads in the world are
like, no no no, you know, uh go high
asset, you know, low obsolescence. Halo
is the new term I keep hearing. Bezos
made I was about to call him Jeff. My
friend Jeff made his money
my buddy.
On a first name basis, guys. He just
doesn't actually know it.
>> [laughter]
>> I mean, Bezos made all his money
by running this playbook. You know, like
you could say the infrastructure they
built out uh digitally with Amazon
became AWS, and the infrastructure that
they built out with the Amazon
fulfillment network is the backbone of
Amazon, and that he, you know, is
whatever a gazillionaire because of it.
And so, to me, it is uh very logical
that somebody who has a bunch of capital
and has made a bunch of money running
that playbook would be like, I think I
can do that again, but maybe even better
with the technology that that's coming.
So,
I mean, we've talked about this before,
but part of being a successful
entrepreneur
is that you're able to kind of look at,
well, what are my skill sets? Like, what
am I like personal um
my personality, my giftings, my talents,
my abilities? What are my assets? You
know, this can be capital, this can be
um experience that I've developed over
the course of my career, could be
industry contacts, whatever, you know,
know-how. And what does that allow me to
do that I can do at a level that other
people can't? And so, if you said, well,
who's going to build the next generation
of warehousing in fulfillment in
America, it's like, I'm betting on Jeff
Bezos. And so, like, for him now is is
Mike Beckham? Should Mike Beckham be
doing that? I don't think so. I mean, I
can do that, and I may do some of it,
but that's not really my primary skill
set, and that's really what you were
talking about, Curtis, and I think that
that is
a good way to frame the entire
discussion here is that
whether or not you take on
manufacturing, whether or not you take
on fulfillment,
is comes back to how are you situated,
what are your skills, what is your
brand,
um and this kind of overlapping set of
factors, and does it make sense in your
particular Venn diagram how all these
things overlap. And for some people,
many people, the answer is no. Like, any
anything that pulls you away from
thinking about marketing and customer
acquisition uh or product is just not
the right focus of your time, and it's a
lower return on your time.
Um there's some people that are able to
do it and turn it into a massive
advantage. And this is why I keep coming
back to the idea that success in
entrepreneurship is as much about
understanding yourself as it is about
anything else.
We to to use a quote that I used last
week, there are many many things where I
am not the best, but there are a few
where I'm situated where I can be one of
the best in the world.
It would be
it would be stupid for me to focus my
time in areas other than those few
things where I can be truly elite. And
that all these we've we've used this
word before, but I like it. Anything
else is just kind of a side quest,
that's just a distraction.
And for operators, the problem is we
like solving problems, we like proving
we can do things, we like taking on
challenges,
and that that can easily work against
you. And so,
maybe this paradigm will be helpful for
people.
Anytime you're trying to take something
on new, hey, is this a main quest or is
this a side quest? And if it's a side
quest, don't do it. You know, like, get
back to the main quest.
>> Is that a leverage thing, Mike? You're
like the the we're always just looking
at where do I have maximum leverage, and
I should probably be putting my time
into those things.
>> Yeah, I mean, one of the ways I think
about it is my capital is
uh not not unlimited, but it's a lot
less limited, but my time is very
strictly fixed.
And that so I have to maximize the
return and the leverage on my time.
To be the most effective version of
myself, I have to. And there's a lot of
my time that's explicitly set aside for
non
monetary reasons. This is I'm spending
time with my wife. I'm spending time
with my kids. I I want to have interests
outside of here. I want to have
friendships, you know, I want to have a
balanced life. I want to be in good
shape. So like there's there's this very
small pie of my week of time. I don't
know what this is. Is it 40 hours? Is it
50 hours? Where it's like this is to be
used to generate economic value. And it
literally can't get any bigger. So the
game is how do I most effectively get
the highest yield out of that?
And the way that you do that starts with
having very clear eyed understanding of
exactly how you're situated, gifts,
skills.
>> Sometimes I don't understand the words
you say, Mike. What is a balanced life?
Like I have no idea what you talked
about.
>> Now, you know, it's actually funny you
say that because I I do kind of hate the
idea of balanced. It's more that
I have multiple success criteria for my
life.
And I don't think there's this idea of
like, okay, I want to spend, you know,
for me to have balance I've got X number
of hours are always going to my family
and Y number of hours are always going
to my yeah, whatever. But I think it's
more that like if on my tombstone, if
it's like you know, he 10 figures in
value. If that's all you have to say,
it's like that's a pretty depressing
tombstone is basically my perspective.
And and then the other perspective I
would give is it is a lot of fun to
build economic value. But I'll tell you
what's really fun is the having people
and relationships and community where
you can use that money to do things. Um
and what's really sad is that there's
some people who are really good at the
economic creation piece, but then they
have nobody to celebrate with, nobody to
spend it with, nobody to give it to, and
that's like a travesty. So, I want to
have that kind of balance. Like, I want
to make a gazillion dollars, but what
makes the gazillion dollars awesome is I
have amazing people that I can go on
vacations with, I have causes I believe
in I can give it to, and I I have a
community that I've been in for a long
time I can invest it in, and to me
that's like winning at life. And like I
just don't know that you can be the best
version of yourself as an operator if
you don't have some kind of definition
of like what is winning in life, and if
that and that has to be at least a
little bit different than winning in
business, I think.
>> Absolutely. Hey Matt, I thought it was a
great question about Jeff Bezos, and I
didn't have an opinion when you said it,
but it doesn't take me long to come up
with an opinion, so I want to say it. I
don't actually read as many books as I
pretend to, but I do scroll a lot on the
internet machine, and I saw him say,
"Hey, I like to invest in things that
take 10 or 20 years that I know are not
going to change in 10 or 20 years.
People are going to want faster service,
not slower. They're going to want better
products, not worse. They're going to
want cheaper products, not
that is happening right now, we have had
deglobalization happen in the last 18
months like we never thought was going
to happen.
The US is very, very well situated to
have the raw materials, the resources,
and the market so that you can
manufacture in your own area with the
right power in order to do this. I think
he's playing a very smart long-term play
of saying, "If we're going to bring
manufacturing back, it's got to be
smart, it's got to be high-tech, it's
got to make the things that are on this,
and it's going to take us 10 years to do
it." Curtis, on this, like the reason
I'm asking the question is
we're we're living through a period of
like pretty significant It feels like
pretty significant disruption. So, like
we're going into a future that
definitely seems a little less certain
than maybe what we've all experienced
over the last couple decades. Like,
we're all old enough to have been in
business now for a while.
And while I love the question of like,
what what's going to be the same in 20
years, I can't help but also ask like,
what won't? Like, what what assumptions
do I have on, you know, what is good
decision-making, good judgment, good
taste, and being an operator that maybe
isn't true anymore because like, the
inputs are changing. You know, Mike, you
sent this article about the whole like,
boil the ocean thing.
Like, that would have been terrible
advice a few years ago. Right? And and
like, to go as an operator, like, the
best advice ever is just focus on one or
two things and do them really well.
And then you tell your teams that, and
that's how you scale up an organization.
And now we're in this place with the AI
where like, no, you can probably boil
the ocean because the nominal cost of
doing everything is going to freaking
zero. What So, I just have to like
I feel like it's I feel stupid asking
the questions because
his- history tells me the answers.
But
I still got to ask them because like,
are the inputs changing? I don't know,
Mike, if you have an opinion on this,
but like
it seems that we should be questioning
everything.
>> I think it's the fundamental skill of
um
I think intellectual curiosity is like a
core life skill.
And I One of my favorite exercises
I think I do this
a lot of days, but in my business, I
certainly try and do it fairly regularly
where
what have I learned in the last week,
the last month, last quarter that I
didn't know before?
And what are all the assumptions that
that might change? What are all the
possibilities that might open up? What
are the Mark Twain once said, it's not
what you know that gets you in trouble,
it's what you know that just ain't so.
And so, the I think when you're
intellectually curious, what it does is
it prevents you from just running on
autopilot with a thing and that's how
you get disrupted. You found a thing
that was successful and you're doing
that thing and you're just doing it,
doing it, doing it and the world around
you is changing, but you're not
reflecting and considering that the way
that that's changed things.
So I'm constantly doing it. I'm
constantly trying to say, "How has
uh the change around me created new
opportunities or changed my perspective
on how I should be doing things, whether
it's my personal life, business,
whatever?"
And right now, I think the the gift of
this particular era of history
is that it's pretty obvious to everybody
that they need to do that.
Like the technology is so disruptive and
it's moving so quickly that um even
people that are not very into tech are
realizing like I need to kind of think
about how this you know interfaces with
my life and how I need to think about my
career and so um I just think we should
always be doing it, but especially now
when the disruption is highest is when
you should be
uh reconsidering your priors the most
and so that's what I'm doing uh with my
business. And uh like what I'm coming
out to is some things are going to
change quite dramatically, the way that
P&L's are structured, the way that
organizations are structured. Like one
of my favorite things I read in the last
week was basically in organizations,
you're either building or you're
selling. That's it going forward. Um and
it's like that's a cool model. That's
very different. Like the middle manager
thing may just be an an idea that's
headed towards extinction.
But uh
there's there's a lot of things that
won't change as well, like you said
earlier, that like we're still going to
need the physical world, right? Like
these products have to sit somewhere
before they go to customers and they're
still going to have to get on trucks or
drones or something and get delivered
there. And that we're still going to
need people that design these products
and take on the mental overhead of
creating companies around delivering
these products to customers and that's
one of the reasons why I think being a
consumer right now is great. Like parts
of us are going to get parts of what we
do are going to get disrupted some, but
there's still going to be a huge need
for what we do.
>> You know, part of this
ability to as we have on the Operator's
Podcast to actually talk to people who
are out there
and building their businesses is I
always do this.
You Ma- Matt, you asked the question
perfectly. It's you've got to be a good
enough person to figure out what the
hell's going on and you got to be
looking at what's coming new, but you
can't be jumpy. You can't jump I read
this, we got to do this. I read this, we
got to do this, right? You've got to
have balance and you've got to be so
curious and aggressive at the change at
the same time. You have to be balanced
not in life, but in business and what
what you're growing. You have to be
saying, I want all the new technology,
but I'm not going to jump from thing to
thing. I've got something that's working
and I've got to build this over there.
And they don't seem like they work
together, but they do. You look back
after 5 years and you're like, "Wow, I'm
glad we didn't do the same thing. I'm
glad we grew, but I'm glad we didn't
chase every trend also." So, I know
that's the hard answer for everyone.
It's like, "Hey, you got to be balanced
when you look at these decisions. Make
them, don't go too deep. If you get into
something bad, get out of it and get
back on track."
So, you know what? The best thing about
this Operator's Podcast to me is I used
to have to watch it
and now I just get to sit here for an
hour and a half and and listen to you
guys give me this wisdom and talk to me
about this stuff. So, I got one last
question for you to end this all up.
What is the one thing you've done in the
last 10 years that 10x'd your business?
Like a simplistic one. We all like to
have people ask us like, "What's the
secret?" No, no, no. What is the one
thing you can look back and say, "Wow,
this 10x'd my business." And I'll tell
you what mine is right now. This
manufacturing that's a pain in the ass
10x'd my business.
It did. And it was really, really,
really hard, but I kind of just kept
doing it year after year and got better
and all of a sudden we got to where we
are and now it's worth it. Now, you guys
are being very thoughtful. You have
something there?
>> I was
uh
spent more money on meta.
Like honestly, like we we we just like
we're a marketing company and we got
really good at it
and we just continue to obsess about it
and that's the lever.
Everything else is kind of in service of
the lever.
That's it. Like it's it's that's the
whole thing.
>> I love it. Some people overcomplicate
it. Yep, that's a great one.
>> Mine is probably I really became an
expert on omnichannel. And at a time
when the world's moving that way and
there's just not many people that are
experts at it. You've got all of the
legacy players that have been in
physical and are trying to figure out
how to do digital and you've got the new
digital companies that are trying to
figure out how to do physical with it
and I just found myself positioned where
I was one of a small number that had
kind of built both simultaneously
and it wasn't a bolt-on. You know,
physical wasn't a bolt-on to digital or
vice versa and that's just really
expanded what's been possible both in
my, you know, Simple Modern and the
companies that uh we've we've added
since then and even in some of the
advising and different things I've done.
I mean, even on this podcast
there are times when the conversation's
really meta heavy where I just kind of
smile and nod because we just don't
spend you know, comparatively we just
don't spend enough on meta for me to
have strong takes. Uh but then there's
other times where we we start talking
about things like omnichannel where, you
know, I I know my voice is the loudest
because I had the most experience. And
so like that that decision um and and I
think that there was this point during
COVID where it's like everything's going
digital and it's like, no, it's not. No,
it's not. Like the the future is hybrid
and so having that skill set has helped
me dramatically.
>> Love it.
Wow, you guys you absolutely killed it.
Thank you so much and everybody who made
it to the end, thanks for watching the
Operator's Podcast. If you're not
somebody who hit the subscribe button,
we don't say that enough. Hit the darn
subscribe button.
Bye.
>> [music]